Guide to the Katja B. Goldman and Michael Sonnenfeldt Collection of Photographs 1900-2002 PR 305
New-York Historical Society
- Series V: 2016 Accruals, 1945-1984
  This series consists of material donated by Katja B. Goldman and Michael Sonnenfeldt in 2016. It includes photographs by Friedman-Abeles, Philippe Halsman, Martha Swope, and Vandamm Studio.
  This series is organized into four subseries arranged alphabetically by photographer's name.
  - Subseries V.1: Friedman-Abeles, 1960-1975
    This subseries consists of photographs of theatrical productions and theatrical portraits taken by Friedman-Abeles. Photographers Joseph Abeles (1908-1991) and Leo Friedman (1919-2011) began their partnership in 1954, with a studio located at 351 West 54th Street in Manhattan. They specialized in documenting Broadway and the theatrical world.
    This subseries is arranged by subject, and alphabetically thereunder.
    - Theatrical Productions: A-D, 1963-1975 (Box 37, Folder 1)
      includes Barbary Shore; Barefoot in the Park; The Divorce of Judy and Jane;Dr. Cook's Garden; Does a Tiger Wear a Necktie?; A Doll's House
    - Theatrical Productions: F-L, 1960-1974 (Box 37, Folder 2)
      Folies Bergere; Lady Audley's Secret; The Last Days Of British Honduras; Little Moon of Alban; The Lincoln Mask; Love and Libel; Lysistrata
    - Theatrical Production: M-S, 1960-1975 (Box 37, Folder 3)
      Mr. President; The Poker Game; A Quarter for the Ladies Room; Rodgers and Hart; Roman Candle; Slag; Squat Betty; A Swim in the Sea.
    - Theatrical Productions: T-Z, 1967-1973 (Box 37, Folder 4)
      That Championship Season; The Tenth Man; Zelda; Zorba.
  - Subseries V.2: Philippe Halsman, 1945-1975
    This subseries consists of portraits taken by Philippe Halsman. Halsman worked for many major American magazines, and his assignments led him to photograph many of the century's leading statesmen, scientists, artists and entertainers.
    This subseries is arranged alphabetically by subject's name.
    - Portraits A-F, 1946-1971 (Box 38, Folder 1)
      Arthur D'Arazian; Mr.[Gerald] Beiser; Robert Bernstein; Thomas E. Dewey; Clifford Brokaw III; Johnny Brokaw; David K. Bruce; Cantinflas; Bill Douce; John Foster Dulles; Joan Evans.
    - Portraits G-M, 1949-1968 (Box 38, Folder 2)
      Jack Goldfarb; Clement Greenberg; Robert Hatfield; Hausman Brothers; Morris Kovinski; Goddard Lieberson; Daniel Longwell; Colonel J.F. Muldrow.
    - Portraits N-R, 1945-1975 (Box 38, Folder 3)
      Dr. Emanuel Neumann; Quesada; Helen Resor; Nelson Rockefeller; James Rorimer; Pete Rose Jr.; Mrs. Bernard [Selma] Rubinstein; Connie Russell; Ed Russell.
    - Portraits S-Z, 1946-1975 (Box 38, Folder 4)
      William Shulton; Konstantin Simonov; Bennett Somberg; Dr. Benjamin Spock; Dr. William B. Terhune; Raymond C. Tower; Mrs. Ira Walfert [Helen Herschdorfer Wolfert]; Dr. Selman A. Waksman; Jerome Weidman; Richard Zanuck.
    - Portraits Unidentified, 1974, undated (Box 38, Folder 5)
  - Subseries V.3: Martha Swope, 1961-1984
    This subseries consists of photos taken by Martha Swope (1928-2017), founder of Swope Associates. Swope was a former dancer who began her photographic career in the 1950s as a freelance photographer specializing in dance and theater. Included here are photos of the original casts of Broadway shows, both in theatrical productions and in the rehearsal process, shot by Swope for publicity and documentary purposes.
    This subseries is arranged alphabetically by the name of the theatrical production.
    - Theatrical Productions: A-F, 1961-1980 (Box 37, Folder 5)
      Ballroom; Drinks Before Dinner; Evita (Chicago); The Fantasticks; Filumena; The Firebugs; Forty Carats.
    - Theatrical Productions H-L, 1961-1984 (Box 37, Folder 6)
      Henry V; Hi Paisano!; How Much, How Much?; Ladies at the Alamo; The Lady from Dubuque; The Last of Mrs. Lincoln; Lorenzaccio.
    - Theatrical Productions: M-N, 1964-1981 (Box 37, Folder 7)
      Madame Aphrodite; Marco Millions; Measures Taken; The Merry Wives of Windsor; The Miser; Moonchildren; Mourning Becomes Electra; Music Is; Music! Music!; My Fair Lady; National Health
    - Theatrical Productions O-R, 1962-1982 (Box 37, Folder 8)
      The Play's the Thing; Plaza Suite; Promises, Promises; P.S. 193; The Queen of the Rebels; Real Inspector Hound; The Ride Across Lake Constance; Streamers; A Streetcar Named Desire; Sugar Babies.
    - Theatrical Productions: S-Z, 1963-1979 (Box 37, Folder 9)
      Vanity of Nothing; Veronica's Room; Walking to Waldheim; Waltz of the Toreadors; What the Butler Saw; Whose Life is it Anyway?; Winning Isn't Everything.
    - Theatrical Productions: 1776, miscellaneous, 1970-1980 (Box 37, Folder 10)
      1776; unidentified productions; portraits of Julie Haydon and Dixie Carter.
  - Subseries V.4: Vandamm Studio, 1936-1960
    This subseries contains the work of Vandamm Studio, founded by Florence Vandamm (1883-1966). Vandamm Studio, in operation in New York from 1924 to 1964, was run by Florence Vandamm and her husband George R. Thomas, and the photographs capture the New York theater world. This subseries includes images of theatrical productions and portraits of stage actors.
    This subseries is arranged by subject, and alphabetically by title/name thereunder.
    - Theatrical Productions: A-L, 1937-1954 (Box 37, Folder 11)
      Abe Lincoln in Illinois; Amphitryon; Another Love Story; By the Beautiful Sea; Come Back Little Sheba; The Corn is Green; Dear Ruth; Duet for Two Hands; Hamlet; Idiot's Delight; Henry IV; King Richard II; Little Dark Horse.
    - Theatrical Productions: M-P, 1936-1960 (Box 37, Folder 12)
      MacBeth; The Madwoman of Chaillot; O Mistress Mine; The Old Maid; One Bright Day; The Pleasure of His Company.
    - Theatrical Productions: Q-Z, 1937-1952 (Box 37, Folder 13)
      Saint Joan; The Sea Gull; The Taming of the Shrew; There Shall Be No Night; To Be Continued; Tovarich; Twelfth Night.
    - Theatrical Portraits: A-Z, 1936-1953 (Box 37, Folder 14)
      Marta Abba; Leslie Banks; George Barber; Norman Bel Geddes; Romney Brent; John Cromwell; Florence Eldridge; John Emery; Lynn Fontanne; Lloyd Gough; Roy Hargrave; William Harrigan; Dennis King; Edith King; Pauline Lord; Alfred Lunt; William Prince; Siegfried Rumann; Cornelia Otis Skinner; Frances Starr; Evelyn Varden; Lucille Watson; Alan Webb; Helen Westley
- Series VI: 2018 Accruals, 1916-1998
  This series consists of material donated by Katja B. Goldman and Michael Sonnenfeldt in 2018. It includes photographs by Friedman-Abeles, Fred McDarrah, Ken Regan and Camera 5, Martha Swope, and Vandamm Studio. It also includes a group of portraits of actors taken by various photographers. Some of these photographers are identified on the verso, while some are unidentified.
  - Subseries VI.1: Friedman-Abeles, 1957-1979
    This subseries contains photographs of theatrical productions and theatrical portraits taken by the Friedman-Abeles Studio. Photographers Joseph Abeles (1908-1991) and Leo Friedman (1919-2011) began their partnership in 1954, with a studio located at 351 West 54th Street in Manhattan. They specialized in documenting Broadway and the theatrical world in the 1950s and 1960s.
    This subseries is arranged by subject, and alphabetically by name thereunder.
    - Theatrical Productions A-D, 1958-1966 (Box 39, Folder 1)
      Any Wednesday; Beekman Place; Beyond the Fringe; Brigadoon; Cabaret; Cold Wind and Warm; Compulsion; Conversation Piece; Conversations in the Dark; Cut of the Axe; The Deputy; Dinner at Eight; Drink to Me Only
    - Theatrical Productions E-H, 1959-1976 (Box 39, Folder 2)
      The Eccentricities of a Nightingale; Ergo; Fair Game; First Impressions; Four Winds; George M!; Godspell; The Great God Brown; The Greatest Man Alive; Hamlet; The Hemingway Hero; Henry V; Here's Where I Belong; High Fidelity; The Hidden River; How to Succeed in Business Without Really Trying.
    - Theatrical Productions I-L, 1968-1972 (Box 39, Folder 3)
      The King and I; King Richard II; Knockout; Lady Audley's Secret; The Last Analysis; Last of the Red Hot Lovers; Leaves of Grass; Leda Had a Little Swan; Little Mary Sunshine; Little Moon of Alban; Live Like Pigs; Lorenzo; Love and Kisses; Love in E Flat; Love is a Time of Day; Love's Labor Lost; Luv.
    - Theatrical Productions M-P, 1958-1976 (Box 39, Folder 4)
      The Madwoman of Chaillot; Man of La Mancha; A Matter of Gravity; Memo; The Memorandum; Merry Wives of Windsor; Midnight Sun; Midsummer Night's Dream; The Milk Train Doesn't Stop Here Anymore; Moon on a Rainbow Shawl; Mother Lover; My Daughter, Your Son; Never Live Over a Pretzel Factory; Never Too Late; Night Life; Possiblities; Purlie.
    - Theatrical Productions Q-T, 1957-1972 (Box 39, Folder 5)
      Rich Little Rich Girl; The Secret Life of Walter Mitty; Seidman and Son; She Shall Have Music; A Shot in the Dark; The Sin of Pat Muldoon; South Pacific; The Star-Spangled Girl; Stop the World I Want To Get Off; Subject to Fits; Sweet Love Remembered; That Championship Season; Three Bags Full
    - Theatrical Production U-Z, unidentified, 1958-1979 (Box 39, Folder 6)
      A Very Rich Woman; Walking Happy; Wanted; The Winter's Tale; The Women; The Woods; The Worlds of Shakespeare; The Wrong Way Light Bulb; You Can't Take it with You; Zorba; Unidentified productions.
    - Theatrical Portraits A-G, 1955-1975 (Box 39, Folder 7)
      Maureen Anderman; Maureen Arthur; Tallulah Bankhead; Keith Baxter; Orson Bean; Barbara Bel Geddes; Ralph Bellamy; Mimi Benzell; Marc Blitzstein; Larry Blydon; Victor Borge; Hanne Bork; Barbara Britton; Susan Browning; David Burns; Jack Canidy; Len Cariou; Helene Carpenter; Gene Castle; Walter Chiari; Peter Coffield; John Colenbach; Wyatt Cooper; Wendy Craig; John Cullum; Irene Dailey; Anita Darian; Danielle Darrieux; Bette Davis; Bruce Dern; Roy Dotrice; Ethelyne Dunfee; James Dybas; Ed Evanko; Monica Evans; Tim Everett; Robert Flemyng; Ruth Ford; Don Francks; Martin Gabel; June Gable; Robert Goulet; Karen Grassle; Kathryn Grayson; Tyrone Guthrie.
    - Theatrical Portraits H-O, 1956-1979 (Box 40, Folder 1)
      Robert Hardy; Donald Harron; Katharine Hepburn; Eileen Herlie; Ron Hussman; Anne Jackson; Henrietta Jacobson; Neil Jones; Judy Kahan; Maria Karnilova; Kurt Kasznar; Patsy Kelly; John Kerr; Daniel Keyes; Nicholas Kepros; Sam Kirkham; Yaphet Kotto; Nicos Kourkoulos; Jerry Lanning; Christine Lahti; Paula Laurence; Alison Leggatt; Sam Levene; Dorothy Loudon; Jonathan Lucas; Fredric March; Hal March; Linda Marsh; Andrea Marcovicci; Nan Martin; Elaine May; Jacqueline McKeever; Siobhan McKenna; John McMartin; Kay Medford; Melina Mercouri; Zia Mohyeddin; Jane Morgan; Robert Morse; Rosemary Murphy; Peg Murray; Julie Newmar; Jill O'Hare
    - Theatrical Portraits P-Z, unidentified, 1956-1977 (Box 40, Folder 2)
      Peter Palmer; Walter Pidgeon; Alice Playten; Josephine Premice; Lex Richards; Viola Roache; Judith Robinson; William Roerick; Carol Rossen; Polly Rowles; Edmond Ryan; Byron Sanders; Dirk Sanders; Gary Springer; David Steinberg; Robert Stephens; Craig Stevens; Michael Strong; Jeremiah Sullivan; Margaret Sullivan; Anthony "Scooter" Teague; L. Thompson; Diane Todd; Harry Towb; Connie Towers; Gene Troobnick; Maria Tucci; Leslie Uggams; Paul Valentine; Joan Van Ark; Diana Van Der Vlis; Eric Van Nuys; Rees Vaughn; Sam Vine; Art Wallace; Billie Lou Watt; Ann Wedgeworth; Ruth White; Ralph Williams; Walter Willison; Bruce Yarnell; unidentified.
  - Subseries VI.2: Fred McDarrah, 1961-1992
    This subseries contains the work of Village Voice photojournalist Fred McDarrah. During his 50-year career at the Voice, McDarrah documented the galleries, lofts, cafes, bars and streets of Greenwich Village and Soho, and the artists, musicians, Beat poets, and writers who populated them.
    - Art and Artists, 1961-1992 (Box 40, Folder 3)
      Artists include Milton Avery, Romare Bearden, Philip Guston, Jack Levine, Faith Ringgold, Larry Rivers, Mark Rothko, Julian Schnabel, and Nancy Spero. Also contains images of Soho art galleries, artworks, and art installations.
    - Film and Music, 1992, undated (Box 40, Folder 4)
      Fanny Ardant and Francois Truffaut, Clive Davis, Nora Ephron and Olvier Stone, Melanie Mayron, Neal and Arthur Rubenstein, Arnold Schwarzenegger, Beverly Sills, Frank Sinatra, Tanya Tucker.
    - Politics, 1967-1968, undated (Box 40, Folder 5)
      Bella Abzug; Albert Shanker leading teacher's union strike march; Dr. Benjamin Spock at Vietnam War protest.
    - Writers, 1975-1978, undated (Box 40, Folder 6)
      includes novelists, playwrights, journalists, art and theater critics. Calvin Tomkins, John Simon, Liz Smith, Jack Newfield, Tom Wolfe, Paddy Chayefsky, William Styron, Budd Schulberg, Nat Hentoff, Irving Howe, Hilton Kramer, Paul Krassner, Kurt Vonnegut, Tom Stoppard, Norman Mailer, James Ivory, Mordechai Richler, Maurice Sendak, George Segal, Patsy Southgate, Gloria Steinem, Studs Terkel
  - Subseries VI.3: Ken Regan and Camera 5, 1965-1990
    - Events, 1969-1973 (Box 41, Folder 1)
      Sally Rand fan dance performance at the Museum of the City of New York; Home With Honor Parade for Vietnam Veterans.
    - Film, Music, and Theater, 1965-1990 (Box 41, Folder 2-3)
      Mikhail Baryshnikov; Candice Bergen; Marlon Brando; Yul Brynner; Truman Capote; Gene Hackman; Gabe Kaplan; Norman Mailer; Al Pacino; Jan Peerce; Tony Perkins; Roberta Peters; Tony Randall; Christopher Reeve; Rolling Stones; Frank Sinatra; Sylvester Stallone
    - Political Figures, 1966-1979 (Box 41, Folder 4)
      Bella Abzug; Meade Esposito; Ted Kennedy with Ed Koch and Hugh Carey; John Lindsay; Richard Nixon; Nelson Rockefeller; Gloria Steinem.
    - Sports, 1969-1986 (Box 41, Folder 5-6)
      Baseball: Mets and Yankees on the field and in the clubhouse. Includes Casey Stengel, Reggie Jackson, and the Mets' 1969 World Series victory celebrations
      Basketball: photos of Wilt Chamberlain, Walt Frazier, a Harlem Globetrotter, and USA vs. Russia 1973.
      Boxing: shots of spectators at the 1974 Ali-Frazier fight at Madison Square Garden, including John F. Kennedy Jr.
      Chess: Boris Spassky
    - Other Images, 1981-1982 (Box 41, Folder 7)
      Ken Pardo; Alexandra Penny; unidentified.
  - Subseries VI.4: Martha Swope, 1964-1989
    - Theatrical Productions A-B, 1964-1989 (Box 42, Folder 1)
      Amadeus; Annie; Arms and the Man; Barnum; Before the Dawn; Beauty Marks; Biography: A Game; The Birthday Party; Black Broadway; Black and Blue; The Boys in Autumn; The Browning Version; Burn This; But for Whom Charlie
    - Theatrical Productions C-H, 1977-1987 (Box 42, Folder 2)
      Colette; The Cover of Life; The Devil's Disciple; Don Juan; Don Juan in Hell; Endgame; The Entertainer; For Colored Girls Who Have Considered Suicide; Francis; the Glass Menagerie; Happy Birthday Mr. Abbott; How He Lied To Her Husband; The Human Comedy.
    - Theatrical Productions I-L, 1970-1987 (Box 42, Folder 3)
      I Ought to be in Pictures; Ice Cream with Hot Fudge; The Iceman Cometh; I'm Not Rappaport; Inheritors; Into the Woods; Jerome Robbins' Broadway; Joseph and the Amazing Technicolor Dreamcoat; K2; King Henry IV; La Cage Aux Folles; Landscape; Landscape of the Body; Last of the Knucklemen; Lenny and the Heartbreakers; The Loves of Anatol; Lullabye and Goodnight.
    - Theatrical Productions M-O, 1971-1987 (Box 42, Folder 4)
      Maggie and Pierre; Marie and Bruce; Mass Appeal; Mastergate; The Master Builder; Master Harold and the Boys; Measure for Measure; The Merry Wives of Windsor; A Midsummer Night's Dream; The Miracle Worker; Miss Julie; Morning's At Seven; My Fair Lady; Non Pasquale
    - Theatrical Productions P-T, 1976-1987 (Box 42, Folder 5)
      Perfectly Frank; Playing With Fire; The Quilling of Prue; Rain; Rats; Romeo and Juliet; Roza; Sparks in the Park; Some Men Need Help; Streamers; A Streetcar Named Desire; The Three Musketeers; Titus Andronicus; The Trouble With Europe; Tru; True West.
    - Theatrical Productions U-Z, unidentified, 1978-1986 (Box 42, Folder 6)
      The Vampires; Wally's Cafe; The Winter Dancers; You Never Can Tell; Zastrozzi; Zoot Suit; unidentified.
    - Theatrical Portraits A-G, 1970-1987 (Box 42, Folder 7)
      Vernel Bagneris; Mikhail Baryshnikov; Carol Brice; Ruth Brown; David Brummel; Ralph Bruneau; Peter Burnell; Alan Castner; Judi Claire; Hume Cronyn; Diana Davila; Sandy Duncan; Ruth Ford; Vincent Gardenia; Kelly Garrett; Robert Guillaume; Whoopi Goldberg; Gawn Granger; Harry Groener; Bob Gunton.
    - Theatrical Portraits H-Z, 1970-1987 (Box 42, Folder 8)
      Uta Hagen; Marian Hailey; Julie Harris; Julie Haydon; Anthony Heald; Tresa Hughes; Leilani Jones; William Katt; Ben Kingsley; Sally Kirkland; Shirley Knight; Cleo Laine; Dick Latessa; Kaiulani Lee; Deborah Malone; E.G. Marshall; Andrea McArdle; Alex Paez; John Peck; Michael Praed; Lee Roy Reams; Jane Russell; Michael Sacks; Robin Strasser; Elaine Stritch; Russ Thacker; Douglas Travis; Tara Tyson.
  - Subseries VI.5: Vandamm Studio, 1935-1963
    - Theatrical Portraits, 1935-1963 (Box 40, Folder 7)
      Shirley Booth and Sidney Blackmer; George M. Cohan; Maurice Evans; Lynn Fontanne; Helen Hayes; Eugenie Leontovich; Helen Menken.
      This subseries is arranged alphabetically by name.
  - Subseries VI.6: Other Studios, 1916-1998
    This subseries consists of portraits of stage and film actors from photographers other than those featured in the rest of the collection. Some of the photographers are identified on the verso of the images, and some are unidentified.
    This subseries is arranged alphabetically by actor name.
    - Theatrical Portraits, 1916-1998 (Box 40, Folder 8)
      Joan Achelis; Bessie Barriscale; Orson Bean; Janet Beecher; Noah Beery; William Bendix; Yul Brynner; Nancy Carroll; Marilyn Cotlow and Frank Rogier; Jane Cowl; Bette Davis; Morton Downey; Mel Ferrer; Judy Garland; Lillian Gish; Robert Goulet; Rose Gregorio; Julie Harris; Josephine Houston; Will Hutchins; Kim Hunter; Kathleen Lockhart; Liza Minelli; Molly Ringwald; Neil Simon; Alexis Smith; Sharon Stone; Joan Tetzel; Grace Valentine; Ruth Weston; Roland Young